https://www.linkedin.com/in/carlosmougan/

## Professional Summary

I am currently a Marie Curie Research Fellow and serve as an Applied Skills Support Advisor at the Alan Turing Institute. I am passionate about predictive modelling and its impact on society. I have worked around the different steps of the ML pipeline: data collection [1], data quality [2], preprocessing [3, 4], modeling [5], and monitoring [6, 7].

At the moment, I am researching model monitoring (distribution shift and xAI) and AI alignment (ethics and political philosophy). I am fortunate to have pursued my passions at world-class research and public institutions. In the past, I have also been a statistician at the European Central Bank, a consultant at Deloitte, and an industry researcher at BBC, BSC, CSIC, Schufa, and AEMET, and a professional swimmer. Since 2017, I have won numerous data science competitions (see 4), ranked Top 2 of 2020 in *DataScienceStackExchange*, contributed to large-open source Python packages category\_encoders and developed my own skshift.

#### EXPERIENCE

# The Alan Turing Institute

London, United Kingdom

Email: carmougan@gmail.com

Mobile:  $+34\ 620\ 618\ 275$ 

Applied Skill Team

- o Principal Investigator: Publication about data quality for research projects at NeurIPS'23 Datasets track [1]
- Advisory Support: I provide academic and industry advisory support in the Applied Skill Team for the Turing Data Study Groups and Turing Internship Network. With a focus on research and industry collaboration, I contribute to the development and implementation of cutting-edge projects between academia and industry.

## Marie Curie Research Fellow

Southampton, United Kingdom

University of Southampton

Feb 2021 - Now

April 2022 - Now

- Phd candidate: Fellowship granted by the European Commission to the Innovative Training Network of NoBias. Publications: NeurIPS'23 [1], AAAI'23 [5], AIES'23 [4], NeurIPS'23 (w) [6], NeurIPS'22 (w) [7], ECMLPKDD'21 (w) [2], IFC [8], MDAI 21 [3], EWAF'23 [9]
- o Schufa Research Visitor: Publication at NeurIPS'22 Workshop [7]
- o University of Pisa Research Visitor: Publication at AIES'23 [4]
- $\circ\,$  BBC DataLab: Aligning and monitoring BBC sounds RecSys with editorial values
- Senior Tutor: Teaching courses on Data Science and ML for industry professionals, consultants and startups

### European Central Bank

Frankfurt, Germany

Statistician - Directorate of Statistics

Jan 2020 - Jan 2021

- Statistician: Monitoring the quality of statistics on the balance of payments and international investment position, as well as methods and sources in the EU Member States
- Machine Learning Engineer: Developed multiclassification neural network for the National Central Banks and European System of Central Banking
- Consulting Management: End to end management of an applied ML consulting project.

## Barcelona SuperComputing Center

Barcelona, Spain

Applied Learning Methods

April 2019 - Aug 2019

• Research Data Scientist: My research focused on machine learning software development for data center optimization and cancer genomics.

CSIC-IIIA

Barcelona, Spain

 $National\ Research\ Council\ -\ Artificial\ Intelligence\ Institute$ 

Jan 2019 - July 2019

• Deep Learning Research Assistant: Improving and applying Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs) to approach large scale combinatorial optimization problems.

# Deloitte Robotics

Madrid, Spain

 $Technological\ Consultant$ 

Dec 2017 - August 2018

- o **Team Leader**: Coordinated a team of two developers, a machine learning engineer, and two data analysts applying Cognitive Automation (CA) to the Audit Process. Implementing ML to the extraction (OCR) and the classification of unstructured data. I took part in the delivery of the project where we were able to improve the efficiency and effectiveness of their operations by a 70%.
- **UiPath Trainer**: UiPath trainer to the international Deloitte's team of Belgium and Netherlands.
- Naoqi Developer: Developing functions for the robots of SoftBank Pepper and Nao for commercial and marketing purposes.
- **Uipath Developer**: Developer for a leading national banking company where we automated two processes. In the delivery of the project, we obtained automation of 100% and 80% respectively.

## **AEMET**

Madrid, Spain

 $National\ Meteorological\ Agency$ 

Sept 2017 - Dec 2017

• Internship: at the Prediction and Modelling Department with a University collaboration, where I modelled and predicted the atmospheric pollution of the northern side of Italy.

#### EDUCATION

### University of Southampton

Phd on Model Monitoring and AI Ethics

Southampton, UK Feb. 2021 - current

• : Model Monitoring in the absence of ground truth data via feature attribution explanations. Supervised by Steffen Staab

#### Universitat Autónoma de Barcelona

Msc in Mathematical Modelling

Barcelona, Spain Sept. 2018 – Jul 2019

Sept. 2018 – Jul 2013

Madrid, Spain

# Universidad Complutense de Madrid

Bsc in Physics

Minnesota, US

Sept. 2013 - Feb 2018

## Saint Paul Preparatory High School

 $International\ baccalaure ate$ 

• Honor International Student at Saint Paul Preparatory: Received a Scholarship for international students with an excellent curriculum (€10,000).

#### OTHER RELEVANT INFORMATION

- Data Science Stack Exchange: Top 2 user in 2020 and top 20 all time Stack Exchange Profile
- Open Source Python Package Developer: Main contributor of category encoders, Main developer of skshift and explanationspace
- Machine Learning Competitions: :1st BCG Gamma Datathon, 1st at Novartis 2021, 3rd Accenture Health Datathon, 2nd at SpainML Telco-churn and Bronze Medal at Kaggle IEEE-CIS Fraud Detection.
- Volunteering with Refugees(Athens) April 2017: Volunteering experience working alongside war refugees trying to improve their environment
- Elite Swimming Athlete 2013 -2017: National recognition for athletes with an outstanding performance. Achievements: Finalist of the Spanish Olympic Trials 2016, 3<sup>rd</sup> Team in Spanish Honor Division, 2012 Minnesota State Champions as Individual & Team. Record holder of several state events.

#### Talks & Presentations

- Royal Society for Spanish Math: Beyond Demographic Parity: Redefining Equal Treatment, Jan 2024
- $\bullet$  NeurIPS: How To Data in Datathons, December 2023
- Regulatable ML Workshop NeurIPS: Necessity of Processing Sensitive Data, December 2023
- AI Ethics and Society Montreal: Fairness Implications of Encoding Protected Attributes, September 2023
- Bias Workshop ECMLPKDD : Fairness Implications of Encoding Protected Attributes, August 2023
- University of Stuttgart: Explanation Shift, June 2023
- AAAI Washington: Monitoring Model Deterioration with Explainable Uncertainty Estimation via Non-Parametric Bootstrap, Jan 2023
- European Central Bank: Desiderata for Explainable AI at the European Central Bank, March 2022
- International Finance Corporation (IFC) workshop on AI: Desiderata for Explainable AI at the European Central Bank, Jan 2022

#### References

- [1] Carlos Mougan, Richard Plant, Clare Teng, Marya Bazzi, Alvaro Cabregas Ejea, Ryan Sze-Yin Chan, David Salvador Jasin, Martin Stoffel, Kirstie Jane Whitaker, and Jules Manser. How to data in datathons. *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems*, 2023.
- [2] Carlos Mougan, Georgios Kanellos, and Thomas Gottron. Desiderata for explainable AI in statistical production systems of the european central bank. In *Machine Learning and Principles and Practice of Knowledge Discovery in Databases International Workshops of ECML PKDD 2021, Virtual Event, September 13-17, 2021, Proceedings, Part I,* volume 1524 of Communications in Computer and Information Science, pages 575–590. Springer, 2021.
- [3] Carlos Mougan, David Masip, Jordi Nin, and Oriol Pujol. Quantile encoder: Tackling high cardinality categorical features in regression problems. In Vicenç Torra and Yasuo Narukawa, editors, *Modeling Decisions for Artificial Intelligence*, pages 168–180, Cham, 2021. Springer International Publishing.
- [4] Carlos Mougan, Jose Alvarez, Salvatore Ruggieri, and Steffen Staab. Fairness implications of encoding protected categorical attributes. In *Proceedings of the 2023 AAAI/ACM Conference on AI, Ethics, and Society*, AIES '23, page 956–966, Montreal, Canada, 2023. Association for Computing Machinery.

- [5] Carlos Mougan and Dan Saattrup Nielsen. Monitoring model deterioration with explainable uncertainty estimation via non-parametric bootstrap. In AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence, 2023.
- [6] Carlos Mougan, Laura State, Antonio Ferrara, Salvatore Ruggieri, and Steffen Staab. Beyond demographic parity: Redefining equal treatment. In First Workshop on AI meets Moral Philosophy and Moral Psychology. Neural Information Processing Systems, 2023.
- [7] Carlos Mougan, Klaus Broelemann, Gjergji Kasneci, Thanassis Tiropanis, and Steffen Staab. Explanation shift: Detecting distribution shifts on tabular data via the explanation space. In NeurIPS 2022 Workshop on Distribution Shifts: Connecting Methods and Applications, 2022.
- [8] Carlos Mougan, Thomas Gottron, Georgios Kanellos, Johannes Micheler, and José Martínez. Introducing explainable supervised machine learning into interactive feedback loops for statistical production systems. In Bank for International Settlements, editor, *Data science in central banking: applications and tools*, volume 59. Bank for International Settlements, 2023.
- [9] Francisco Castillo-Eslava, Carlos Mougan, Alejandro Romero-Reche, and Steffen Staab. The role of large language models in the recognition of territorial sovereignty: An analysis of the construction of legitimacy. In *European Workshop of Algorithmic Fairness*, 2023.